Great, now that's how you have a basic understanding of Pandas and you know how to use the Jupiter Notebooks
we can go ahead and learn how to load various kinds of files in Python using Pandas and Jupiter.
So I've got five files here and they contain exactly the same data sets.
This is a text version or let me open of the Excel version that will show a pretty overview of data as you
can see.
So we've got seven lines of code including the header.
We have also seven columns.
So it's just some basic data of supermarkets. The address, city, state country and the name of the supermarket
and number of employees.
And similarly we have exactly the same data but in a different format.
So we have CSV and CSV means comma separated values.
So it's basically a text file where the values, the columns are separated by commas as you can see
here.
So every column is supported by a comma but it has a CSV extension and it can be open with Excel.
.
So if I open this now you'll see the same data so that you saw in Excel file.
We also have the same data separated by say my columns.
As you can see in here. And yeah if you're working with data you're probably familiar with this
kind of files.
So this is how to store data you need to have some conventions and using such convention then you
use other programs such as Python to load these data.
So when you load a CSV file Python knows that the values will be separated by commas and it knows how
to separate them.
It knows how to extract values.
So we will open all of these one by one.
We also have adjacent file
which is yet another format to store data and looks like a python dictionary actually.
So we will learn how to convert them to Pandas data frames as well.
So all these will be converted to Pandas data frames.
Yeah go ahead and start Jupiter. Jupiter Notebook. Here are my files.
I'll go ahead and create a new Jupiter Notebook for Python 3.
Before I go ahead and load those files in Python there is a trick I do usually, I import os
and then os.listdir and ALT Enter.
Execute that. You go to the next line.
And what you get is you get a list of files and folders as well of file names that you have in
the current directory.
So no I don't have to switch to my folder to look at the names.
I have everything in here.
Now I can go and import Pandas and let's start loading these files one by one.
Let's say df1 so dataframe one that would be equal to pandas.read_csv and then you have to pass
the name of the file that you want to open supermarkets.csv and just Enter.
Maybe you want to print that out. Df there.
We got an error.
Let's see why. It says supermakets does not exist.
Yeah I forgot
an R here just there. This time it worked.
Dd to delete that cell and what we got here is
So we loaded the first and then we printed that out.
So we got this table, nice table in there.
That's how easy it is to load data from a CSV file.
Now if you see this, this is in bold the first row there that's a special row.
So that's a header of your data frame and Python Pandas was able to automatically recognize the header
from your file.
So this method, the Read CSV Method that has a header parameter that is set to True by default.
But if you want you can set it to none.
And that's how you tell Python that my data don't have a header.
So what Python will do is it will treat your first row of your file as a simple row
so it will just dump it amongst the other rows and what it will do it will create a default header
for your data frame with numbers.
So I'm going to remove this
and leave it as it was. Notice that we also have an ID column there which if you want you can use it
as an index for your data.
So if you want to use IDs and index instead of letting Python define your index what you do is you
apply the Set Index Method to your data frame and then you say ID there Execute.
Well Python will do it.
It will search for the column with name ID and you will set it as an index. Df1.shape if you
want to know the shape of your data frame.
So you get 6 7 meaning that you got sixrows and seven columns including the ID column.
And you know that's how you load CSV files.
Now let's go ahead and load df2.pandas.
What's next?
Well next is JSON.
So instead of doing read_csv we you want to do read_json and then you just pass the name of your JSON file
including the extension of course. I executed that. I forgot to print that out. Si this a JSON file
.
And similarly if you want to you can set index to ID and execute again.
And ID set as 		an index.
Now you can also notice that the order of the columns is not the same as the previous CSV file that
we opened which is not a problem.
Every column has its own name its own identity.
So having call them of those in order it's not a problem.
And let's go ahead and load the xls file xlsx actually an Excel file.
So pandas.read_excel and
you pass the name of the Excel file.
Normally you should also pass another parameter here for Excel files.
Because you know Excel files might have multiple sheets inside them.
So you want to specify the sheet name which start from zero so you need to pass the index actually.
If you want the first sheet you want to pass 0 if you on the second sheet you want to press 1 and so
on.
So I'll pass zero there.
I had only one sheet in the Excel file. Df3 execute.
And yeah, we were able to successfully read the Excel file as well.
Let's move on with that txt file.
So it's supermarkets separated by commas.
So it's a little structure separated by commas. For that
So for the txt files separated by commas
again use a read_csv.
Just like that df4.
And here is the data frame. So this supermarkets.csv
actually some say it's a comma separated file but to be more accurate you would say are character
separated values. So C is for character.
And you know there might be different characters there.
In this case when you have commas as separators you don't have to pass any separator parameter here
but when you have other values as separators you will have to pass that. That is the next scenario.
So df5 pandas.read_csv.
So we're talking about supermarkets semi-colons or supermarkets_semi-colons.txt.
So let me try this.
as it is now.
So if I execute that Python will not be able to recognize the semi-colon there.
The reason for that is because
the separator parameter has a value of comma by default.
So you want to change that to your separator which is a semi-colon in this case. Execute. We've got
an error there.
Unexpected.
Argument separator.
So it seems like read_csv doesn't have a separated, separator parameter.
In that case you want to do to ask for help. So here is the parameters that you want to pass.
So it's actually a sep and you can see that the default value of sep is a comma.
So you close that and go to here.
Change that to sep execute.
And here is the data frame.
Great.
What's left to d? Yeah.
Well we consumed everything.
That's about reading local files.
Now Pandas also allows you to read online files directly from the web.
For instance here we have a CSV file in this website so I browsed to that and then it was
downloaded.
And if you want to you can go ahead and put that in your Jupiter folder and then open it as we did.
Or you can grab this URL go here say df6.read_csv and then pass the URL  just there.
Df6 to print that out.
Boom.
Here is the foil.
So is the same exactly the same CSV file that we opened earlier up but we were able to gather from
the web.
Similarly you can get all the files as well.
JSON. You can pass it as URL.
Just there and print that out.
And here is the file.
So this can be very useful when you want to automate things.
Let's say you have some data from a web site from a data provider or maybe you have multiple files
and you want to write a loop in Python that accesses these URLs and then it gets the data.
And also you then analyze the data and so on.
So yeah that's about loading a data in Python via Pandas and using Jupiter.
So I believe you find this very easy and yeah we'll move on and do some data analysis in the next lectures.
So I'll see you there.