And yeah, let's close this section on Pandas by looking at a real world example and in this example
what we're going to do is we're going to grab the address of each of these rows that we have in the data
frame and we're going to convert it to latitude and longitude coordinates.
So geographic coordinates in other words. Now addresses they define unique points on the Earth.
So if you pass this address to some service lets say you throw it on Google Maps and Google Maps will
point to you so it will generate a marker that will tell you where this point is located.
Now on the background that marker actually has a pair of latitude and longitude coordinates and
every point on Earth has these pair of coordinates.
And if you follow the section on building web maps with Folium in the course
and you know what this latitude and longitude how
they come in handy
when you build applications such as web maps or other maps. Now the process to convert from
addresses to coordinates
it's called geocoding.
And if you want to convert from latitude and longitude to adresses that is called the reverse geocoding.
In this lecture how we were going to be looking at geocoding.
So basically what we'going to do is we add here a column to the data frame.
Actually two columns one for latitude and one for longitude for each of the rows.
Now Pandas cannot do that directly.
So you need the help
of another library that is called Geopy and you can install Geopy with pip, so pip install
and Geopy and just wait a while.
Oh great.
And then you know before going ahead and applying the geocoder to my data defraying values I'd like
to actually convert a single address, an address string with geocoder. Something you should be aware of
is that to use Geopy,
actually to use the geocoder which is you know if you say import Geopy, and then if you say Geopy
like that, you'll see that you have a geocoder module among them which is this one here, geocoders
actually. And for the geocoders to work
You need an internet connection because what geocoders will do it will get your address and then
it will send that to an online service that has all of these addresses in a database and then for your
address it will calculate the corresponding latitude and longitude.
So you need an internet connection and yeah what you normally do is you know you want to import from
geopy.geocoders import,
actually there are a few geocoders there, but we will use Nominatim which is a tool of Open Street maps and what
to do is you know you create a Nominatim variable object so you store that object in a variable. That
would be equal to the Nominatim class.
So like that.
And once you have that object then you pointed to the geocode method
of the Nominatim object and you pass an address as a string in there.
Lets say 3995, twenty third, and then maybe the city, and the zip code 94114. If you execute that you'll get a location
data type.
So all these, and all that includes is you know, it includes the address that you passed there.
So this one and it has also added United States of America so the country in here, and you also get
the latitude and longitude.
This one that you just ignore that.
It's just a response from the geocoder so it doesn't mean much.
Now sometimes though is rare, sometimes you may get a None object.
So for instance if you pass this address which probably is not a real address, I'm not sure about that.
I don't know, but if you say San Francisco
CA for 94119. If you execute that nothing will happen and actually you can see that if you store that in a variable
and then print, this will say that it's a None object so it doesn't have anything inside.
So yeah be aware of these scenarios as well.
And yeah we had our working address, this one here.
Let's store that in this variable. And once you have that to extract the latitude and longitude you apply latitude
for the latitude value and longitude for the longitude, and that should do it because you know n, type n is
a special object it's called a location object of Geopy.
So you need to apply those methods and yeah, that's how you convert an address string to a location or to latitude
and longitude values.
But how about converting an entire column of the data frame into latitude and longitude? So we've got this
data frame, df equals to pandas.read.csv.
And this should be an underscore.
Let me import Pandas first and print out the data frame.
So this is our new data frame.
Actually this is the old one that we've been using.
We have five six addresses there, six rows with an address, city, and state, and country.
Now the geocode method more or less it accepts this kind of format, so it expects from you the road name
name in here, and then the city, and then the zip code in,  and the country.
So what we can do is we need to construct such a column you know different first.
Yeah you can either create and you call them or you can add it to an existing one.
So let's say I added the address of the existing address code so that it would be able to G.F. address.
So there's value in here.
Plus I'll need a comment there.
So Komal maybe a space plus if City sort of comma between address and city and then another color and
then close the it again and yet another Kumo like that.
Plus again DMF and a lovely country that's Should duty to.
We've got a complete address column in there.
Great.
Now we need to send this string to the GOP code methods and we need to do it for all the shows.
You're probably thinking of its rating but with pandas actually you don't need to iterate Pappas is
designed in a way that it allows you it has some Mathilde's that allows you to apply a method or a function
to all the rows of defrayed without having to write a formal loop and to do that you know you need to
create and you call them let's call it coordinates where you store the stream.
You know this stream you service.
Actually it's not a stream it's a location object but you get it in your data frame.
So we need to store locations for each of the rooms and the way you do that is you know you points to
the column that you want to pass to your geocoder and then we use a painless method called applied.
So what method do you want to apply to the values of the address column.
Well that be.
And so and is nominate him object that we have here also creates knowm so SOOOO that it be known that
G.O. code is soooo the same as this one.
So the joke code but in this case you don't pass is there because of the applying method.
It will do it for you.
So just like that and then you maybe you print of data or bring in there and see what you get.
I got the service timed out.
Geocoder is not working probably.
Maybe I have a problem with my internet connection.
So if you get this long after that is not your fault.
A It's always a problem with a geocoder with a pie.
I'll try that again.
I know this time it works.
It was able to fetch the location objects in here.
I mean you cannot see the last doing a long.
Because it's a long string.
But if you do it like that you see you you get the serious four coordinates and your vet is not showing
it either.
But you can do it's like you know the coordinates and new X is the first item on it like that.
And then you get the entire text for the location pure on the latitude you get latitude only that brings
us to the point that you may want.
Now to add another two columns and you did it for him.
I went to fetch the latitude and longitude values.
So all the different frame is this one.
At the moment.
What you can do is you know you could create a letter to call them that would be called The F coordinates
ploy.
You know you cannot apply latitude directly
because you get this kind of error that say Sirius has no latitude.
So you're applying a latitude method to a serious but a series doesn't recognize that we're serious
to recognize.
So they apply methods.
So you can write your other methods now all latitude will point to the two values.
All of these coordinates column and in the scenario you use you use a lambda function.
So which is an inline method to be of the function.
So you say lambda x x is a temporary variable then you say X latitude I know let's keep it like that
for for now.
Yes.
There let's see what we've got.
Well it's so that's a non type object has no attributes latitude.
So this can be quite tricky if you're not experienced with geocoding.
Another reason we get this is that we have a known row value in there among our rows of our row which
is not a location data type and does not have a latitude Meffert because you know what we did here is
we are storing all these values.
So it is like a loop.
We are storing all these values in the temporary x variable and for each of these value we apply velocity.
So what point on we'll do is it will go through the first row and it will apply the latitude to the
first row and it is sorted in the latitudes column and then it goes to the second value.
But in this value latitude does not exist for now.
So you get an error that you could apply conditional and in line if conditional You say X is not tails.
And I know it's a bit confusing but what we did is you know poor Let's do if x is not None.
So it will apply this method for sorrow's for those values otherwise it will store none either current
cell or the latitudes colon.
So that is clear.
I'll ask you here.
Yeah you got the latitude to call them in there.
Great.
And we can do the same for all longer tudes
along with tudes and here as well.
That was quick.
And you know that's it I think you have a lot to do and longer to call them in your data.
So please have a second look at what I wrote in here and if there is something that doesn't make sense
just drop a question and I'll be happy to answer you.
So yeah we have quite a lot of flexibility working with data frames.
I hope you enjoy this.
I'll talk to either next lunchers.
So you.